大家好，我是《每日宇航员》频道的Tim Dodd
Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd, The Everyday Astronaut.
有一个问题不但我自己问过
Here's a fun question that not only have I myself asked
还有好多人问过我
but I actually get asked this quite often.
为什么我们经常听到“开始滚转”、“滚转程序完成”等播报
Why do we hear a call-out like "roger roll" or "roll program complete",
同时看到火箭沿X轴旋转？
at which point we see the rocket rotate or roll on its x-axis?
开始滚转、滚转检查、滚转执行完毕
Roll commence, clear. Roll checks out. Roll program has commenced.
我觉得最好的例子就是航天飞机了
The best example of this, I think was the Space Shuttle
它有非常明显的大幅度滚转程序
which had a really obvious and really dramatic roll program.
当它飞离发射塔时
As soon as it cleared the tower,
你能注意到它在进行很明显、甚至有点吓人的滚转
you can see it making a very impressive and sometimes, scary-looking roll.
或许这样的机动对于航天飞机这样不对称的载具倒还算合理
Now, a maneuver like this makes sense when a vehicle's asymmetrical like a space shuttle
但像Saturn V、Titan、Atlas、Delta IV这些柱状的火箭
but why do cylindrical rockets like Saturn V or Titan or Atlas or Delta IV,
为啥也要进行滚转呢？
why do they even bother doing a roll
为何火箭就不能简单地拐弯
and can't rockets just tip over
执行一些俯仰、偏航的操作，直接指向要飞的方向？
and go in whatever direction they need to go, do a little pitch here, a little yaw there,
只要指向它想飞的方向
as long as the pointy end is going in the direction it's intended to go,
谁会管火箭哪面朝地哪面朝天？
who cares which side of the rocket is facing the earth and which side is facing space? Right?
那么今天，我们将首先定义俯仰、偏航、滚转，及其对应在火箭上的方向
So today, first we'll define the pitch, yaw, roll and their corresponding axes on a rocket.
之后我们将开门见山地揭示火箭滚转的原因
Then we're gonna dive into why a rocket rolls in the first place,
观察发射方位角与发射轨迹的关系
take a look at launch azimuths and the relationships to trajectories
然后我们还将了解一些独特的对正方向角的方法
and then we'll look at some unique solutions to orientations,
包括一些发射时不进行滚转来对正轨迹的火箭
including some rockets that don't roll on ascent to line with their trajectories at all.
我们走起吧
Let's get started.
这是我很喜欢的话题
This is one of those topics I love,
因为原因可能会很难猜
where at first, the reason feels kind of perplexing
但当你听到一个解释后你就马上拍大腿
then you hear one explanation you're like oh,
“啊有道理哈~”
I guess that makes sense
然后你又听到另一个解释，学习了这些边边角角的知识后回头一看
but then you think of some other reasons and learn of all these weird little edge cases and come to find out
发现这里的门道还真不少
there's actually a lot to unpack here.
另外要澄清一点
And just to clarify things,
我们今天要说的是火箭的滚转程序，不是重力转向
we're specifically talking about the roll program of rockets and not their gravity turn.
这是两个完全不同的东西
These are two totally different things.
我们要说的是这个
We're focusing on this,
不是这个
not this.
这个
This,
不是这个
not this.
那么我们首先了解下俯仰、偏航、滚转，及其对应在火箭上的方向
So let's start off with a quick overview of pitch, yaw and roll and how they correspond on a rocket.
大家可能听说过俯仰、偏航、滚转这三个词
You may have heard the terms pitch, yaw and roll,
尤其是在聊飞机的时候
especially when talking about airplanes.
对于飞机，俯仰指的是机头拉起或者压低
On an airplane, pitch is the nose pulling up or diving down.
偏航是机头向左或向右
Yaw's the nose going left or right
而滚转，你可以想象机头不动、翼尖上下移动
and roll, you can think of the wingtips going up or down while the nose stays in the same place.
对于飞机来说，定义俯仰、偏航、滚转很容易
With airplanes, it's really easy to define pitch, yaw and roll
因为飞机有很明显的外形特征
because airplanes have really obvious characteristics
比如机翼、起落架、驾驶舱、尾翼等
like wings, landing gear, a cockpit and a vertical stabilizer.
你可能就会奇怪，对于柱状的火箭怎么定义这些方向呢？
And you might think how do you define these dimensions on a cylindrical rocket?
虽然火箭是非常对称的
Although a rocket is pretty symmetrical,
定义这些方向仍然是很重要的
it's still vital to define these dimensions.
不然火箭可能想往东飞结果一路向北之类的
I mean, otherwise, your rocket might go north instead of east or something.
所以我们在KSP中拿出一架飞机，去掉机翼和尾翼
So let's take a jetliner and just remove the wings and tail stabilizer.
哇，机舱看起来和火箭一样液~
Hey, look, the fuselage kind of looks like a rocket, perfect.
这时我们还是有俯仰、偏航、滚转的
So now we still have our pitch yaw and roll.
然后把它竖起来
We just stand this baby up on its tail and let it rip.
当年把驾驶舱放在洲际导弹顶上就是这样的
This was literally true when cockpits were put on missiles
像东方号、水星号、双子号、联盟号都是这意思
which is basically, all the Vostok, Mercury, Gemini, Soyuz programs were.
现在火箭推上发射架
So now with a rocket on the launch pad,
我们从驾驶舱看还是有相同的俯仰、偏航、滚转
we can look at the cockpit for that same pitch, yaw and roll.
坐在驾驶舱，俯仰就是你当前的机头上下移动，即绕Y轴旋转
When sitting in the cockpit, your pitch or your nose up and down is rotating on the y-axis,
偏航就是机头左右移动，即绕Z轴旋转
yawing, left or right is rotating on the z-axis
左右滚转就是绕X轴运动
and rolling left or right is on the x-axis.
与飞机不同的是，火箭的俯仰、偏航、滚转不是由机翼控制的
Unlike an airplane, the pitch, yaw and roll of a rocket, generally isn't controlled by wings or fins
而是由发动机本身控制的
but it's actually controlled by the engine itself
通过一个有矢量、有时是辅助推进器来帮助控制滚转
via a gimbal and perhaps some auxiliary thrusters to help control roll.
而机翼、小翼有时会在大气内用于稳定火箭
However, wings and fins are sometimes used for stability in the atmosphere.
火箭底部只放一台发动机的时候
A single engine on the bottom of a rocket
只能提供两个方向的控制：俯仰和偏航
can only provide two axes of control; that's pitch and yaw.
因为发动机推力方向会通过火箭的重心
And this is because the engine goes through the center of the rocket.
所以它只能提供两个方向的扭矩
Because of that, it can only apply torque on two axes.
于是为了让绝大多数单发动机火箭拥有滚转控制
So in order for most single-engine rockets to have roll control,
我们会发现火箭外围会有一些辅助推进器
you'll normally see auxiliary thrusters stuck on the side or the outer perimeter of the rocket.
这些辅助推进器叫“游机”
These auxiliary thrusters are called vernier thrusters
我觉得游机在原版Atlas SM-65 A火箭上看最明显了
and I think they're the most obvious on the original Atlas SM-65 A rocket
联盟号火箭的底部也有几个游机
and there's several vernier thrusters on the bottom of the Soyuz Rockets as well
但有些单发动机火箭更聪明，它们使用燃气发生器的废气控制滚转
but some single-engine rockets get clever and control their roll via the gas generator exhaust
比如Delta IV、Delta IV Heavy火箭上的RS-68发动机
like the RS-68 on the Delta IV, Delta IV Heavy.
你会发现工程师机智地把两个燃气发生器废气出口放在发动机两边来控制滚转
You can see the engineers cleverly point
and steer the dual gas generator exhausts on each side of the engine for roll control.
如果你想复习一下燃气发生器循环和开式循环
Now if you need to brush up on gas generator cycles and the open cycle,
我最近做了一起视频讲解了几款主流的发动机循环方式
I recently did a really in-depth rundown of a few common engine cycles
标题是《SpaceX的猛禽是最强火箭发动机吗？》
in my Is SpaceX's Raptor Engine the King of Rocket Engines video.
拥有至少两台发动机或者至少两个燃烧室的发动机的火箭
Both rockets that have at least two engines or at least two combustion chambers
比如Atlas V上的RD-180发动机
like the RD-180 on the Atlas V
可以让两台发动机指向不同方向产生绕X轴的滚转
you can point the engines in opposite directions which will induce your x-axis roll.
好，现在我们知道了火箭可以如何控制自己滚转
OK, so now that we know how a rocket can control its roll,
那我们开始解释为何火箭需要控制滚转
now we can get into why a rocket needs to control its roll.
首先就是火箭需要在飞行中保持稳定
Well, to begin, a rocket needs to remain stable throughout the flight
以免其转的太快把自己转散架
so it doesn't spin so fast it tears itself apart.
当然啦，这是火箭需要控制其滚转的最基本的原因了
Okay, sure, that's the most basic reason of why the rocket needs to control its roll
但我们还是不知道为何火箭在离开发射架后要刻意进行滚转操作呢？
but we still get to the question why do they intentionally roll once they get off the launch pad?
滚转完成……
Roll complete and…
我要开门见山地告诉你原因
So I'm gonna tell you the reason here
然后我将深入解答，并定义一些新东西
then we're gonna dive in and I'm going to define a few more things.
火箭需要滚转来让自己对正其飞行的方向角
The rocket rolls to align itself to its flight azimuth
使其飞行轨迹(的控制)变成一个简单的俯仰控制程序
so its flight path becomes a simple pitch program.
是不是感觉这句话背后有很多要说的？
We have a lot to unpack in just that one sentence, huh?
那首先咱们先讲讲方位角
So first, let's talk about the azimuth.
由于各种载荷的目标轨道的不同
Now, depending on the destination of the payload,
火箭需要对准一个非常确定的某条轨道
rockets need to head to a very specific orbit
还要提醒大家的是
and a fun reminder here,
去太空肯定要向上飞，但想要留在太空
I like to say to go to space, you go up but to stay in space,
则需要横向飞，而且要非常非常快
you need to go sideways really, really fast,
所有的轨道都是这样的
which really, that's all orbit is.
想要到达目标轨道
And now, to get to your desired orbit,
就需要火箭指向一个特定且非常精确的方向
you wanna make sure that that sideways part of your flight
is pointing in a very, very specific and accurate direction.
如果火箭从赤道向正东发射
Now if you were to launch a rocket right on the equator, straight east,
不但会完全利用地球自转线速度带来的速度优势
not only would you take full advantage of the Earth's rotation
which gives the rocket a nice little boost
还会进入一个倾角为零的轨道
but you'd also place your vehicle on a zero degree inclination.
就像地球赤道上的光环一样
It's like a nice little belt around the earth's equator
另一个有关倾角的例子是国际空间站
or another fun example of inclination is the International Space Station
倾角51.6度
which is on a 51.6 degree inclination.
这个倾角可以刚好让俄罗斯参与其中
Now it's on this exact inclination so the Russians can participate
且发射时不需要把助推器扔到中国境内
and they can launch without dropping boosters on China
更不需要为了对接来个狗腿机动
or without doing a costly dogleg maneuver.
另外作为参考，如果火箭从肯尼迪航天中心向正东发射
And just as a reference, if you launched straight east, out of Kennedy Space Center,
会进入一个28.6度倾角的轨道
you'd be on a 28.6 degree inclination
而这正是肯尼迪航天中心的纬度
which you may notice is the exact latitude of the Space Center.
这里就要引入方位角的概念了
So here's where we get to what your azimuth is.
方位角就是你在发射台拿一个指南针
The azimuth is basically if you're holding a compass on the launch pad,
那么如果你想飞向预定轨道，你需要向哪个方向飞？
which direction do you want the rocket to go to get to your desired orbit?
这里我们先停一下，澄清一件事
But we should pause here for a second and clear up one thing
因为这让我有点混淆
because this definitely confused me a bit.
要明确方位角和倾角的不同
Let's be sure and note the difference between the azimuth and the inclination.
方位角是驾驶舱里导航球的指向
The azimuth is what's on the nav ball inside a cockpit.
正北是0度、正东是90度、正南是180度、正西是270度
North on the nav ball is zero degrees while East is 90, South is 180 degrees and west is 270.
这和倾角完全没关系
Now this does not line up with the inclinations.
零度倾角是赤道正上方向东飞行的轨道
A zero degree inclination is due east on the equator
极地轨道是90度倾角的轨道
while a polar orbit is inclined 90 degrees
另外，可发射的最小倾角取决于你的纬度
but again, minimum inclination depends on your latitude.
所以只有当你在赤道时向正东飞行才会进入零度倾角的轨道
So flying due east will only correspond to a zero degree inclination if you were launching on the equator.
还要记住，所有顺向轨道，或者说和地球自转方向相同的轨道
And another side note, all pro-grade orbits or orbits that follow the rotation of the earth
倾角都在0到90度之间
are between zero and 90 degrees inclination.
即使火箭向南飞过赤道它倾角也是0到90度
If the rocket is flying south from the equator, it's still between zero and 90 degrees
因为倾角单纯是轨道面和赤道面的夹角
because inclination is really just a measure in degrees how far off angle the orbit is from the equator.
当然了，实际情况远没这么简单
And of course, it's not quite just as simple as this.
如果想进入51.6度倾角的轨道和国际空间站对接
If you wanna go to 51.6 degrees and rendezvous with the International Space Station,
实际的指向并不是51.6度
you don't actually point at 51.6 degrees.
你实际会指向大约45度
You actually point at about 45 degrees
但这些就涉及到一些数学计算来考虑到地球的自转和球面几何了
but now we're getting into some kind of fun math that takes into account the Earth's rotation
但这些就涉及到一些数学计算来考虑到地球的自转和球面三角了
and spherical trigonometry
这对于本期视频来讲就说的太远了
which might be getting a little too far into the weeds for this video.
现在我们知道火箭去不同的目标轨道会往不同方向飞
So now that we know that rockets don't all follow the same path to get to space into their destinations,
那我们就获得些许火箭刻意滚转原因的线索
we're starting to get some of the puzzle pieces as to why they might intentionally roll.
下一条线索，我们就来看看发射台本身
For our next clue, we need to look no further than the launch pads themselves
而我们刚刚提到了Saturn V和航天飞机
and since we've mentioned rockets like the space shuttle and the Saturn V,
那我们就说说全世界最著名的发射台
let's take a look at one of the most famous launch pads in the world;
一个见证了这两款火箭无数次飞行的发射台
a launch pad that saw lots of launches from both these vehicles
而现在，从那发射的是太空叉的Falcon 9和Falcon Heavy
and now, SpaceX's Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy,
没错，我说的就是肯尼迪航天中心的LC-39A
of course, I'm talking about Launch Complex 39A at Kennedy Space Center.
LC-39A是个绝好的例子，因为它四个方向恰好对准东西南北
LC 39A is a great example because it's perfectly lined north, south, east and west.
看看这张图
Take a look here.
我们可以看到火焰导流槽和航天飞机运输车(Crawler)的轨道恰好是南北方向的
We can see the flame trench and the crawler way perfectly runs north and south.
先从土星五号说起
So let's start off with the Saturn V
其于1967年11月9日从LC-39A首飞
which first launched from 39A on its inaugural test flight on November 9th, 1967
最后一次发射是1973年5月14日的天空实验室任务
and last launched Skylab on May 14th, 1973.
火箭推出到发射台时，可以发现脐带塔在火箭的北面
With vehicle crawled out on the pad, you'll see the launch umbilical tower on the north side
登船臂从脐带塔伸出连接到火箭的东侧
with its crew access arm that swings around and connects to the east side of the rocket.
宇航员从那里进入火箭，并且在登船后
This is where the astronauts get in and once they're in,
他们头向东、脚向西
they're facing, with the top of their heads, due east and their feet, due west.
当然，除了指令舱以外
So of course, along with the command module,
火箭其余的部分也有各种东西连接
the rest of the vehicle had certain features
比如连接火箭和脐带塔的燃料、电力脐带
such as the fuel and electrical umbilicals that connected the rocket to the launch umbilical tower,
里面有很多外部电缆管道等重要设备
had some external raceways which had some important wiring and all that kind of stuff
但重要的是，当讲到火箭的指向时
but most importantly, when talking about the alignment of the rocket,
有一个东西叫IMU
was a thing called the IMU.
IMU全称设备单元，位于Saturn V三级顶部
The IMU or the instrument unit sat on top of the Saturn V's third stage
里面有火箭的制导系统
which housed the rockets guidance systems.
包括一台数字计算机，在当年体积相当大
This included a digital computer, pretty big deal at the time,
一台模拟飞控计算机，加速度计和一些陀螺仪
an analog flight control computer, accelerometers and some gyroscopes.
当Saturn V要飞向月球时
So in the case of the Saturn V heading to the moon,
发射方位角是72度，也就是东偏北18度
the launch azimuth was 72 degrees which is 18 degrees north of due east.
所以在发射台时
So while on launch pad,
飞行轨迹和火箭本身有18度的夹角
the flight path and the belly of the rocket were 18 degrees off from each other.
这就是需要滚转程序的第一个原因
And here's where we get to the first reason for the roll program.
与其移动整个发射台来让火箭对正那18度的夹角
Now instead of moving the entire launch pad to just face the belly of the rocket at that 18 degree angle,
不如让火箭简单地执行一个滚转操作
the rocket could simply perform a roll
来消除飞行轨迹和火箭自身坐标系之间的夹角
to basically zero out the difference between the flight path and the body's physical coordinates.
当上述两者夹角变成零以后
It would have a value that's a nice easy zero.
火箭只要控制俯仰就行了
Now all the rocket has to do is pitch over.
这让计算机需要计算的数值从两组变成了一组
This made it so the computer really only had to calculate one set of numbers instead of two,
让数学计算变得容易许多
making the math and the calculations much, much easier.
更少的变量是件好事
Less variables equals a good thing.
简单点从没错
It's nice to keep it simple.
另一个物理上的考虑是“万向节死锁”
Another physical consideration is a thing called gimbal lock.
万向节可以绕三个维度自由旋转
Now gimbals can freely rotate on all three dimensions
并且可以在空间中固定指向一个方向
and align themselves to a fixed position in space
从而告诉制导计算机当前载具的指向
which can then tell the guidance computers where the vehicle is pointing.
当你消除某一个参数的时候
Now, by zeroing out one of those numbers,
万向节就会处于最不可能死锁的状态
you're keeping the gimbal as far away from potential gimbal lock as possible.
而万向节死锁是非常非常糟糕的
And a gimbal that locks up can be a very, very bad thing.
为了演示一下为何消除火箭的滚转方向是个好事
So in order to demonstrate why zeroing out a vehicle's roll is a good thing,
我们在KSP里快速捏一个火箭
let's just build a quick rocket in Kerbal Space Program.
默认情况下捏出来的火箭是正好对准东西南北四个方向的
Now by default, when you build a rocket, it's aligned perfectly north, south, east and west
俯仰对应南北方向
with pitch aligned north and south
偏航对应东西方向
and yaw aligned east and west.
为了进入零度倾角的轨道
So to head out on an equatorial zero degree inclination orbit,
你只要按一个D键向右、向东偏就行了
you need to press only a single key the right amount and in this example,
that is the D key which will yaw over due east,
一指开火箭，牛逼吧
one finger flying, nice and easy.
接下来我们把原来对正的火箭旋转20来度
Now let's rotate the rocket about 20 degrees or so away from being perfectly aligned
继续尝试向正东方向飞行进入零度倾角的轨道
and still try and follow that perfectly zero degree inclination due east.
当然啦，这对于像我这么才华横溢天赋异禀的人来说也不难
Now this can still easily be done when you're super, super talented like me, obviously
但这次你要改用两个键来控制了
but all kidding aside, you're only using two keys this time
难度明显提升
but it is noticeably harder.
所以为什么不简单点呢？
So why not just keep it simple?
接下来是另一个很有意思的思想实验的例子
Well here's another example that's a fun thought experiment.
这是爱荷华州滑铁卢的地图
This is a map of Downtown Waterloo, Iowa.
你会发现街道都是东北-西南和西北-东南走向的
Notice that the streets run from northeast to southwest and from Northwest to Southeast.
它们没有与东西南北对正，而是与河流对正
And they're aligned to the river and not aligned to true north.
而如果你在这个城市，你会不由自主地把东西南北坐标变成这样
Now if you're walking around, it's
probably unlikely that you wouldn't just redefine your own coordinates in your head
在脑中把东北想象成河的“北”
and start thinking of anything on this side of the river as north
而对岸是“南”
and anything on this side as south.
不用费劲去想“东北、西南”这些会让导航更加方便
It just makes navigating a lot easier than thinking about northeast and southwest.
所以如果火箭和发射台经常是保持固定的位置
So if the rocket and the launchpad are always in a fixed position which,
剧透一哈，大多数发射架都是固定方向的，这点我们稍后会补充
spoiler alert, they pretty much always are, well, kind of, we'll talk about that more in a second;
那么最简单的就是给火箭编程，让它自己滚转来对正方向角
the easiest thing to do is to program the rocket to do a quick roll to align itself with its azimuth.
这让导航从三维的方程变成了二维的方程
This takes the navigation from being a three-dimensional equation to just a two-dimensional equation
可以极大减少变量、降低复杂度
and removes a ton of complexity and variables.
看上去微不足道但蚊子再小也是肉
I know it doesn't seem like much but it definitely matters.
当然，说火箭是俯仰还是偏航就太较真了
Now of course whether the vehicle pitches or yaws is a bit pedantic
毕竟这都是人为规定的东西对吧？
because doesn't someone just define that.
那接下来要说的就是两者之间另一个重要的区别
Well, there's still some other important distinctions.
还说阿波罗，在发射台上宇航员头朝东
Sticking with Apollo, the astronauts heads were pointing due east on the launchpad.
而那个方向其实是土星五号的“肚子”
They were actually on the belly of the Saturn V.
而有趣的是
But here's a fun fact.
你们知道土星五号的指令舱和火箭本身有完全相反的Y、Z坐标轴吗
Do you actually know the command module in the Saturn V had exactly opposite y and z coordinates.
我不太明白具体原因，但的确很有意思
I don't exactly know why but I think it's kind of interesting.
而这也意味着当火箭俯仰机动后
But this meant when the rocket pitched over,
指令长可以透过保护罩上的小窗观察外面
the commander could look out the small port window in the blasts protective cover
得到他们当前姿态的目视参考
and get a visual reference of their orientation.
所以当火箭滚转后
So by zeroing out the roll,
窗外的地平线刚好是水平的
the horizon would appear across the window
以此作为参考会更加简单
which made it easy to use as a reference.
而假如指令长看到外面的地平线突然抬起或者旋转起来
This also made it so if the commander saw the ground suddenly coming up or the horizon spinning,
那他们就该考虑是否要终止发射了
they may have considered aborting
或者说他们起码有一个很好的目视参考来决定是否终止发射
or, at least, had a good visual reference on whether or not that'd be necessary.
另一个经常要确定火箭“肚子”方向的原因是
Another reason why there's usually a defined belly of a rocket
是为了把雷达天线、接收机放在最优的位置
is to place the radio antennas and the receivers in the optimal place
以保证在起飞时与地面有最佳的通信质量
to have best contact with the ground during ascent.
航天飞机就是最典型的例子
This is especially true with the space shuttle
如果起飞时轨道器放在外挂燃料箱上边
which if it had ascended with the orbiter on top of the external fuel tank,
信号收发就会大打折扣
it would have had a much worse line of sight.
而说到航天飞机
When we're talking about the space shuttle,
它的独特外形让它的滚转程序则显得更为重要
it's roll program was even more necessary due to its unique shape.
不但因为那是让机翼和机身结构承载外挂燃料箱的最佳选择
Not only was it structurally the best option for the wings and the struts holding the external fuel tank
还因为轨道器在外挂燃料箱下方的飞行姿态
but by flying with the orbiter in the wake of the external fuel tank,
可以提升20%的运力
there was actually a 20% increase in payload capacity.
同样，虽然多数火箭长相相对航天飞机更加对称
And although most rockets look relatively symmetrical,
它们表面仍然有很多凸起结构
they almost always have some kind of protruding feature.
比如说土星五号
Take a look at the Saturn V,
它的外表面有很多凸起
it had very large bumps and bulges on the outside
在发射程序中那些凸起都是不能忽视的
that definitely aren't insignificant when factoring in the ascent profile.
你会发现这些地方是附加的管路或线缆
You'll see these areas where additional piping or wiring is housed inside sections called raceways.
你们可以发现猎鹰九号和重型猎鹰的每个一级两侧有两个不同的线缆管道
You notice there are two different raceways on each side of the Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy cores.
也能根据这个不同看出重型猎鹰两侧的一级火箭其实是相互180翻转的
You can tell the two outer cores of the Falcon Heavy are 180 degrees opposite each other
because of those two different raceways
回到航天飞机
but back to the space shuttle.
航天飞机是通过固体火箭助推器的矢量喷嘴来控制其俯仰和滚转的
The shuttle controlled its pitch and roll via gimbaling nozzles on the solid rocket boosters.
诚然，航天飞机的主发动机也有矢量喷嘴，范围还不小
Yes, the main space shuttle engines could gimbal too and gimbal a lot
但它们主要作用是确保推力方向穿过重心
but they primarily gimballed to maintain the center of thrust going through the center of mass.
通过使用固推来控制俯仰
By using the solid rocket boosters to control pitch,
两个推力矢量方向相对于重心保持对称
the gimbal vectors are in line with each other, relative to the center of mass.
可能会让控制更加容易
This probably makes it easier to control.
这也关系到像重型猎鹰、Delta IV重型这样的多芯级火箭
This is also relevant to multi core rockets like the Falcon Heavy and the Delta IV Heavy
它们也都有滚转程序，让芯级的摆放对准飞行轨迹
which both have a roll program which again, aligns the cores kind of perpendicular to the flight path.
这可能不是啥大事
Now, this might not be a huge deal or not
但我们考虑一下这类的火箭
but let's just take a look at a vehicle like this
如果它们飞行时一排发动机是垂直于地平线摆放的
and if it were flying with its engines in a roll perpendicular to the horizon,
那么位于最上面和最下面的发动机
the engines that are on the top and the bottom
将会相对于中央的发动机来说对火箭产生不同的杠杆作用
would have a different amount of leverage over the vehicle
compared to that center engine or center core.
所以虽然我不敢肯定
So I'm not entirely sure
但我认为这可能是让多芯级火箭平行于地平线飞行的某个原因
but I think this might be another reason why they normally fly pretty parallel to the horizon
而这类火箭另一个平行地平线飞行的考虑可能是关于分级
but they also fly with these rockets flat to the horizon for stage separation
因为这样两侧的助推有最小的概率撞上中央的芯级
so the boosters have the lowest chances of hitting the center core.
既然说到了太空叉的重型猎鹰，那么接下来要说的有意思的事情是
So now while we're on the topic of the Falcon Heavy and SpaceX, here's a fun little fact.
猎鹰九号和电子号都不进行滚转程序来对正其方位角
The Falcon 9 does not perform a roll program to align to its azimuth and neither does the Electron rocket.
猎鹰九号和电子号火箭都只进行所需的俯仰、偏航机动
Both the Falcon 9 and the Electron just pitch and yaw over however much is necessary
只为一些气动上的考虑和其他少量因素而进行滚转
and roll for aerodynamic considerations and a few other variables as well.
但在真实的3D空间控制火箭其实比听起来难得多
But controlling a rocket in a true 3D space like this is actually a lot harder than it sounds.
耗费了好几届学生的心血才解决了其中线性代数的问题
It took a generation of grad students to actually solve the linear algebra
火箭也需要算力足够强的计算机
and have access to computers powerful enough on the rockets
才能实时解算这种类型的控制
to do this math in real time for this type of control.
所以如果猎鹰九号和电子号不需要滚转，那它们为何要滚转呢？
So if the Falcon 9 and the Electron Rockets don't need to roll, why do they?
呃……答案是为了好玩
Well, apparently, for fun.
老马你又逗我
So I totally got trolled here by Elon
但在2019年6月12日
because on June 12, 2019,
太空叉发射了三颗来自加拿大宇航局的卫星
SpaceX launched a trio of satellites from the Canadian Space Agency.
在起飞后，猎鹰九号进行了一个很明显的滚转机动
Soon after liftoff, the Falcon 9 did a pretty substantial roll.
的确，火箭不是对称的
Now, again, rockets aren't actually symmetrical
而且尽管猎鹰九号可以同时控制俯仰和偏航
and although the Falcon 9 can navigate along both axes,
这次任务中这样的滚转操作很有可能是出于载荷上的考虑
it's likely that this particular launch had a roll like this due to some payload considerations.
客户方面可能有某些限制
Customers might have certain constraints
而该次发射的载荷是不对称放置的
and with this particular launch having an offset payload,
可能他们需要火箭以某种特定姿态飞行
perhaps they needed to fly it in a certain way
来让载荷以“更好的面貌”迎接发射的G值
for the payload to best handle the g-forces.
而猎鹰九号还有些许不同的是
The Falcon 9 is also perhaps little unique
那就是在一二级分离时必须摆正方向
and that it for sure wants to be oriented correctly at stage separation.
这样一级火箭上的氮气推进器才能让一级翻转回来
So the first stage has both of its nitrogen thrusters able to help do that flip maneuver.
因为猎鹰九号只有两组冷气推进器，呈180度摆放
Since the Falcon 9 has only two packs of cold gas thrusters that are 180 degrees apart from each other,
这意味着如果火箭旋转了90度
this means if the vehicle rotated 90 degrees,
那两组中就只剩一组推进器能让一级翻转了
only one set of thrusters could help with the flip instead of two.
另一个有趣的事情是
Here's another fun story.
你们看过最早期的猎鹰九号发射吗？
Have you ever seen the very first Falcon 9 launch?
它会在起飞后迅速无意地旋转近45度
It unintentionally rolled almost 45 degrees immediately after takeoff.
原因是其发动机的燃气发生器尾气带一个小角度
This was due to the gas generator exhaust that has a slight angle to it.
就好像Delta IV火箭用RS-68的燃气发生器滚转一样
So just like how the Delta IV's RS-68 uses its gas generators to roll,
九台梅林发动机的燃气发生器的扭矩实在是太大了
the nine Merlin engines had so much extra torque from the gas generators exhaust,
火箭本身的矢量要整整一秒才能抵消这个滚转
it took a second for the engine gimbals to cancel the roll out.
火箭滚转的另一个考虑是整流罩分离
And one more reason why Rockets roll is for the fairing separation.
我不知道让整流罩按Y轴向分离还是Z轴向分离的具体考虑是怎样的
Now I don't exactly know what considerations go in
to choosing whether the fairing would split on its y-axis or its z axis
但我肯定会提，因为这一定是考虑因素
but it should be noted that this is definitely taken into consideration.
从目前我能看到的来说
For instance, from what I can tell, at least,
太空叉喜欢沿着Y轴、上下方向分离整流罩
SpaceX tends to ditch their fairings on its y-axis or up and down
而ULA喜欢沿Z轴、左右方向分离整流罩
while ULA tends to ditch its fairings off to the sides on its z-axis.
这两家分离方向不同的具体原因何在？
Why exactly each launch provider chooses to ditch them in this manner,
我不知道，但至少提一下，挺有意思的
I'm not sure but it's kind of fun to note.
所以21世纪的火箭终于有能力取消滚转对正方向角这样的操作
So a few 21st century rockets finally took the roll to align to the azimuth program out
但或许我最喜欢的不进行滚转机动的火箭是苏联的火箭
but perhaps my favorite rockets that didn't roll align were Soviet era rockets.
还记得我最开始说移动整个火箭和(或)发射架来对正方向角太难了吗？
Remember near the beginning,
还记得我最开始说移动整个火箭和(或)发射架来对正方向角太难了吗？when I said it'd be too hard to turn the rocket and/or the launch pad to align with its trajectory,
而这正是苏联为他们R-7家族的火箭，比如联盟号，想到的解决办法
well that's actually exactly what the Soviet Union came up with for their R-7 family of rockets like the Soyuz.
没错，联盟号的整个发射架都可以旋转来让火箭对正其发射方向
That's right, the entire launch pad of the Soyuz actually rotates to align the rocket up with its azimuth.
这样的弊端是你的发射方位角可能在你的发射窗口内有些许变化
Now some downsides to this is your azimuth might change ever so slightly throughout your launch window
而通过旋转发射架来对正方位角的办法
so by aligning the launch pad to your azimuth,
会让你的发射窗口、发射轨迹不那么灵活
you might lose some flexibility in the launch window and flight path.
这也是新款联盟号所改进的，因为它有了数字计算机
This is something the new Soyuz too can do away with now that it has a digital flight computer
现在它能自行修正方位角了
and it can now align itself on the correct azimuth.
但载人任务使用的仍然是联盟-FG火箭
Although crewed missions still use a Soyuz-FG
所以仍然要使用可旋转发射架
which utilizes that rotating table but lastly,
但还是有一款非常先进、非常超前于时代的火箭
there was still perhaps the most advanced, most ahead of its time rocket,
那就是苏联的N-1超级烟花
the Soviet Union's N-1 rocket
其设计是同时控制俯仰和滚转来发射入轨，虽然最后都变成烟花了
which was meant to, never did, follow its flight path using both pitch and yaw.
火箭本身有滚转控制推进器
It had some roll control thrusters
在前三次发射中都太小了
that were undersized for the first three launches
在第四次发射中升级了
and then upgraded for the fourth launch
但它们全都不是用来对正发射方向角的
but they weren't used to align to the azimuth.
它们只用来稳定
They were just used for stability.
唉，真希望它没有变成烟花啊
I still really wish the N1 had worked out.
多牛逼的火箭啊
It's such an awesome rocket.
于是我们总结一下，火箭滚转有以下几个原因
So to summarize, rockets roll for a few reasons
就像所有的火箭科学等工程学一样
and like all rocket science and engineering,
这样做肯定有好处，那具体原因呢——
there's actually some good reasons but as for why,
简言之就是用滚转来对正方向角比旋转发射架更简单
well, it's generally easier to roll to align the vehicle to its azimuth than it is to move the launchpad.
这让制导计算机计算起来更简单
It makes for easier calculations for the guidance computer.
火箭会出于气动、结构上的考虑而滚转
Rockets roll for aerodynamic and structural considerations.
火箭为了让宇航员有更好的目视参考而滚转
They roll for the astronauts' vantage point and visual references.
火箭为了对正整流罩分离时的姿态而滚转
They roll for fairing deployment orientation.
火箭为了对正调姿推进器而滚转
They roll to align auxiliary or control thrusters
火箭为了更好的视野从而有更好的通信质量而滚转
and they roll for best line-of-sight for communications and down links.
所以这样的回答大家满意吗？
So does this help answer that question?
这就是另一个有趣的事情了
It's another one of those fun things
你知道这样做肯定是有好处的
where you probably know there's a good reason
但你就是说不清道不明这每一条原因都是啥
but it's just kind of hard to find all those good reasons.
所以我希望这能让大家理解
Hopefully, this helps us appreciate
每天工程师和科学家要为这些琐碎而重要的决定而掉多少头发
just how many of these little
but important decisions engineers and scientists need to come up with every single day.
一切不同寻常的事情背后必有原因
There's always a reason for all the strange little quirks.
如果你有其他问题有关火箭滚转程序、或者有关火箭
Let me know what other questions you have about roll programs or rockets
或者有关火箭科学的，欢迎在评论区留言
or rocket science in general in the comments below.
我这的清单它又长又宽
I have a crazy long list
我还在为这些新视频忙里忙外
I'm still trying to chew a way out here for videos
所以不要放松，有你们慢慢学的呢！
so stay tuned, there's still a million things to learn.
非常感谢我的Patreon赞助者
I owe a huge thank you to my Patreon supporters
他们在我的Discord频道为本期视频的校对作出了巨大贡献
for literally being right here in my Discord Channel
right now still fact-checking a few things in this actual video.
所以如果你也想来帮忙校对或者寻找一些有趣的话题
So if you like to help fact-check or find little fun quirks
或者想提出反馈建议
and do all these other things like provide feedback for videos
想为下期视频内容投票之类的
and have voting on upcoming videos and things like that,
请务必考虑去Patreon为我赞助
please consider becoming a Patreon member
你可以进入我们独家的Discord频道
where you'll gain access to our exclusive Discord Channel,
看到独家直播内容、进入独家的reddit子版块
exclusive live streams and our exclusive subreddit
链接就在下方
by going to patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
真的，谢谢啊
Seriously, thank you.
没有你们的赞助就没有这期视频
I couldn't make these videos without my Patreon supporters.
上网的时候也顺便看看我的网店
While you're online, definitely check out my web store
能买到比如这件全流量分级燃烧循环的T恤
where you can find things like this full four stage combustion cycle shirt
等各种其他新东西
and a ton of other new things.
也别忘了我不爱按需求去印这些东西
And don't forget, I actually do runs of shirts now. I don't do like print-on-demand.
所以你如果看到喜欢的衬衫
So if you see a shirt that you like,
可能一个月内都没货
it might not be there in a month.
所以一定要常来看看
So just keep that in mind and stop back often,
尤其新品到货的时候
especially as new releases come out
卖的贼快
because they can sell out really quickly
另外你还能听听我的音乐
and while you're there, you can listen to my music too
点击左边音乐标签就能去iTunes或者Spotify上听
by clicking on the music tab or listen to it on iTunes or Spotify.
我视频里的音乐几乎都是我的原创
Everything in my videos is always original music
所以记得去看看，大热天去听听小曲多好
so check it out, put it on a playlist for the summer.
把你的想法告诉我
Let me know what you think.
感谢各位
Thanks everybody, that's gonna do it for me.
我是《每日宇航员》的Tim Dodd
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut,
把太空知识带给寻常百姓家~
bringing space down to earth for everyday people.